Guide to the Donald E. Knuth papers SC0097
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Addenda, 2001-078, Accession ARCH-2001-078
  - MMIXware
    - MMIX-PIPE, 5 February 1999 – draft (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - MMIX-PIPE, 16 February 1999 – draft with documentation of the MMIX hardware as it existed at the time (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - MMIXware, 13 April 1999 – earliest surviving drafts of MMIX-ARITH and MMIX-SIM (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - MMIXware, 19 April 199 – earliest surviving drafts of MMIX-IO and MNOtype with current versions of MMIX-SIM and the MMIX documentation (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Fascicle 1, 8 May 1999 – first galley proofs of new expository material for The Art of Computer Programming (section 1.3.1') (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Fascicle 1, 26 May 1999 – galley proofs, including section 1.3.2' (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Fascicle 1, 8 June 1999 – galley proofs, now including section 1.4.1' (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fascicle 1, 21 June 1999 – galley proofs, including sections 1.4.2' and 1.4.3', and first draft of index and glossary (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Fascicle 1, 27 June 1999 – galley proofs of first complete "clean" version (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fascicle 1, 23 August 1999 – Knuth's working reference copy (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - CTWILL – text for CTWILL program (version 3.43) and companion programs REFSORT and TWINX (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - MMIX-ARITH – proofmode output of program MMIX-ARITH dated 27 September 1999, with handwritten corrections, and book pages dated 2 October 1999 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - MMIX-CONFIG – proofmode and book pages (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - MMIX-PIPE – proofmode and book pages (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - MMIX-SIM – proofmode and book pages (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - MMIXAL – proofmode and book pages (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - MMIX – proofmode and book pages (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - MMIXware front matter and short chapters (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - MMIXware correspondence with publisher Springer-Verlag, 1998-99 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Joy of TeX, A Gourmet Guide to Typesetting Technical Text by Computer by Michael Spivak, Ph.D. [with annotations], 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Addenda, 2001-235, Accession ARCH-2001-235
  This accession pertains to the lecture series on the general topic of faith and science delivered at MIT in the fall of 1999, which resulted in the book Things a Computer Scientist Rarely Talks About. Included are correspondence, notes, transcripts of the taped lectures, drafts, and illustrations.
  "Materials from a unique episode in my life, when I was asked to give a series of six public lectures at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) on the general topic of faith and science. The lectures, delivered in the fall of 1999, were broadcast live on the Internet, and I'm told that tens of thousands of people watched them. Each 90-minute lecture consisted of a prepared talk followed by an impromptu question-and-answer session, with about 45 minutes devoted to each portion. Transcripts were made from the videotapes and I edited then during the summer of 2000, adding notes and references to the literature. They were published in 2001 by Stanford's Center for the Study of Linguistics and Information (CSLI), with the title "Things a Computer Scientist Rarely Talks About"--which was also the general title of the lectures when I gave them originally. A complete archive of that book appears here."
  - Correspondence regarding lectures, including email announcements of the lectures and some of the typical feedback, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes the original letters of invitation, letters about practical details of moving to Massachusetts, email announcenents of the lectures themselves, and some of the typical feedback received from the audience.
  - Lecture 1: Introduction– notes and brochure, 1999 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    The page of handwritten notes I used while preparing the first lecture, fol1owed by the notes I used during the Lecture itself. Also the widely distributed brochure that had been used to announce the series.
  - Lecture 2: Randomization and Religion-notes, 1999 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The notes I used to prepare and deliver the second lecture.
  - Lecture 3: Language Translation– notes and overhead transparencies, 1999 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    The notes I used to prepare and deliver tbe third lecture, together with overhead transparencies used to illustrate it. (Included are several dozen additlonal transparencies that I had made just in case they night be needed when I was answering questions from the audience.)
  - Lecture 4: Aesthetics– notes, 1999 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The notes I used to prepare and deliver the fourth lecture. This lecture was illustrated by 35mm slides, see Folder 17 below.
  - Lecture 5: Glimpses of God – notes and copy of Raymond Smullyan's story "Planet without Laughter," statistics about "key verses" of the Bible, and an email from Douglas Hofstadter re "laughter yoga", 1999 Dec 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The notes I used to prepare and deliver the fifth lecture. Also includes a xerox copy of Raymoud Smullyan's short story "Planet Without Laughter"; statistics about so-called "key verses" of the Bible and some materials collected subsequent to the lecture: an obituary of Raymond E. Brown; email from Douglas Hofstadter re "laughter yoga"; and an excerpt fron George Buttrick's lectures on Biblical Thougbt and the Secular University.
  - Lecture 6: God and Computer Science – notes and relevant sources, 1999 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    The notes I used to prepare ald deliver the sixth lecture, including several magazine articles and other relevant materials found on the Internet (e.g., Einstein's renarks on Science, Philosophy and Rellgion).
  - Panel discussion: Creativity, Spirituality, and Computer Science, 17 – notes, 1999 Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
    The single page of notes I used during that session.
  - Raw transcripts (from videotapes of the lectures) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    The videotapes of all six lectures and the panel discussion were transcribed by staff members of Dr. Dobb's Journal, the company that did the webcasts. These transcriptions, though riddled with errors, provided a good basis fron which I could attempt to recreate the feeling of the original lectures (while watching the videotapes several times myself).
  - Half-baked transcripts (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This is how the transcripts looked after I had converted them to simple ASCII text format and inserted time coordinates to correlate them with the videotapes. My editing of the lectures essentially began here.
  - Illustrations – includes original proofs of TV frames, poster illustration, and 35mm slides; and first proofs after conversion to black-and-white (Box 1, Folder 11)
    One of the interesting tasks I faced was to convert videotape frames to illustrations that could be used in the book. The quality of video data is insufficient for large pictures, so I decided to render each image at the largest size that would retain reasonably sharp details. This limited me to slightly nore than 1 inch in each dimension, so it strongly affected the design of the book. The original pictures shown here in black and white were actually in color when viewed by computer, but color did not add anything important. Indeed, when I edited the pictures later, converting then to black and white, the lack of color made it possible for me to enhance nany details that would have looked strange if I had distorted the colors in a similar fashion.
    This folder contains: Original proofs of captured TV frames; An experinent with TV frames printed in color (fron the paael discussion); 0riginal proofs of the Poster illustration (scanned in parts); Original proofs of inages taken from 35mm slides; First proofs after conversion to black-and-white.
  - First drafts for lectures 1-6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    The result after initial editing of the "haIf-baked transcripts", showing many handwritten editorial changes and the places where illustrations are to be inserted. (These drafts cover Lectures 1-6 on1y. The first draft of the panel discussion was emailed to other panelists on 15 April 2000; see folder 16 below.)
  - Second drafts, with illustrations (Box 2, Folder 1)
    The result after inserting all illustrations (ear1y July 2000); this was shown to several readers asking for comments.
  - Comments from the copy editors (Box 2, Folder 2)
    After a few changes to the drafts in Box 2, Folder 1, the copy editors made numerous further suggestions.
  - Near-final copy (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Most of the copy editors, suggestions, and further corrections noticed on rereading, 1ed to these pages, which were used to prepare the index.
  - Correspondence re publication, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    The bumpy road to publication of a complex book such as this is well documented by this sequence of more than 100 letters.
  - slides used in lecture 4, 48 computer file(s) (pcd)
    The 35mm slides used in Lecture 4, converted to digital form, appear on this conpact disk in several sizes.
  - Hand-bound proof [missing lecture 5, pages 138-166], April 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    A xerox-copy mockup of the book, several copies of which were sent to potential reviewers. Also contains a few last-minute changes, especially to the index.
- Addenda, 2004-044, Accession ARCH-2004-044
  - Selected Papers on Computer Languages
    - CL1, Chapter 1: The Early Development of Programming Languages (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Copy of original article; correspondence and additional references used to prepare the addendum; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL 2, Chapter 2: Backus Normal Form versus Backus Naur Form (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Copy of original article; edited version
    - CL3, Chapter 3: Teaching ALGOL 60 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Copy of original article; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL4, Chapter 4: ALGOL 60 confidential (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - CL5, Chapter 5: SMALGOL-61 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - CL6, Chapter 6: Man or Boy? (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - CL7, Chapter 7: A Proposal for Input-Output Conventions in ALGOL 60 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Copy of original article; subsequent correspondence; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL8, Chapter 8: The Remaining Trouble Spots in ALGOL 60 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Copy of original article; correspondence; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL 9, Chapter 9: SOL – A Symbolic Language for Systems Simulation (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - CL10, Chapter 10: A Formal Definition of SOL (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - CH11, Chapter 11: The Science of Programming Languages (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Copy of old manuscript notes; manuscripts for newly added material, including computer programs to check the examples; edited version
    - CL12, Chapter 12: Programming Languages for Automata (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - CL13, Chapter 13: A Characterization of Parenthesis Languages (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - CL14, Chapter 14: Top-Down Syntax Analysis (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - CL15, Chapter 15: On the Translation of Languages from Left to Right (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - CL16, Chapter 16: Context-Free Multilanguages (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - CL17, Chapter 17: Semantics of Context-Free Languages (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Copy of original article and errata; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL18, Chapter 18: Examples of Formal Semantics (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - CL19, Chapter 19: The Genesis of Attribute Grammars (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - CL20, Chapter 20: A History of Writing Compilers (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Copy of original article; errata; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL21, Chapter 21: RUNCIBLE – Algebraic Translation on a Limited Computer (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Copy of original article; worksheets to make the illustrations; marked galleys; manuscript for supplementary material; edited version
    - CL22, Chapter 22: Computer-Drawn Flowcharts (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - CL23, Chapter 23: Notes on Avoiding 'go to' Statements (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Copy of original article; errata and correspondence; marked galleys; edited version
    - CL24, Chapter 24: An Empirical Study of FORTRAN Programs (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - CL25, Chapter 25: Efficient Coroutine Generation (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Edited version (This article was composed for a festscrift publication that actually didn't appear until 2004.)
    - CL26, Miscellaneous scraps: (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Proof of frontispiece; first draft of the index; correspondence re index
    - CL27, First printout of entire book, chapters 1-8 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - CL27, First printout of entire book, chapters 9-14 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - CL27, First printout of entire book, chapters 15-21 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - CL27, First printout of entire book, chapters 22-end (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Selected Papers on Discrete Mathematics
    - DM01, Chapter 1: Combinatorial Analysis and Computer (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - DM02, Chapter 2: Two Notes on Notation (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - DM03, Chapter 3: Bracket Notation for the 'Coefficient of' Operator (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - DM04, Chapter 4: Johann Faulhaber and Sums of Powers (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - DM05, Chapter 5: Notes on Thomas Harriot (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - DM06, Chapter 6: A Permanent Inequality (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - DM07, Chapter 7: Overlapping Pfaffians (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Copy of original electronic publication; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM08, Chapter 8: The Sandwich Theorem (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Copy of original electronic publication; correspondence; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM09, Chapter 9: Combinatorial Matrices (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Copy of original electronic preprint; correspondence; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM10, Chapter: Aztec Diamonds, Checkerboard Graphs, Spanning Trees (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - DM11, Chapter: Partitioned Tensor Products and Their Spectra (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - DM12, Chapter: Oriented Subtrees of an Arc Digraph (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - DM13, Chapter 13: Another Enumeration of Trees (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - DM14, Chapter 14: Abel Identities and Inverse Relations (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - DM15, Chapter 15: Convolution Polynomials (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - DM16, Chapter 16: Polynomials Involving the Floor Function (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - DM17, Chapter 17: Construction of a Random Sequence (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - DM18, Chapter 18: An Imaginary Number System (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - DM19, Chapter 19: Tables of Finite Fields (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - DM20, Chapter 20: Finite Semifields and Projective Planes (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - DM21, Chapter 21: A Class of Projective Planes (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - DM22, Chapter 22: Notes on Central Groupoids (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Copy of original article; correspondence; computer programs and articles used for supplementary material; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM23, Chapter 23: Huffman's Algorithm via Algebra (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - DM24, Chapter 24: Wheels Within Wheels (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - DM25, Chapter 25: Complements and Transitive Closures (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - DM26, Chapter 26: Random Matroids (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Copy of original article; correspondence; computer programs used to check examples; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM27, Chapter 27: The Asymptotic Number of Geometries (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - DM28, Chapter 28: Permutations with Nonnegative Partial Sums (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - DM29, Chapter 29: Efficient Balanced Codes (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Copy of original article; reprint of paper used to prepare addendum; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM30, Chapter 30: The Knowlton\with Graham Partition Problem (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - DM31, Chapter 31: Permutations, Matrices, Generalized Young Tableaux (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - DM32, Chapter 32: Enumeration of Plane Partitions (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - DM33, Chapter 33: A Note on Solid Partitions (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Copy of original article; computer program used to check the algorithm; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM34, Chapter 34: Identities from Partition Involutions (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Correspondence; computer program; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM35, Chapter 35: Subspaces, Subsets, and Partitions (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - DM36, Chapter 36: The Power of a Prime... (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - DM37, Chapter 37: An Almost Linear Recurrence (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - DM38, Chapter 38: Recurrence Relations Based on Minimization (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Copy of original article; reprint of related article; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM39, Chapter 39: A Recurrence Related to Trees (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - DM4, Chapter 40: The First Cycles in an Evolving Graph (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - DM41, Chapter 41: The Birth of the Giant Component (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Copy of original article; correspondence;; computer programs and results used to correct the originally reported data; marked galleys; edited version
    - DM42, Miscellaneous scraps (Box 7, Folder 2)
      List of chapters and number of errors caught by spell-checker; proofs of some illustrations; list of names to complete for the index; first draft of the index
    - DM43, First Printout of Entire Book (Box 8)
- Addenda, 2011-200, Accession ARCH 2011-200
  - Selected papers
    Materials accumulated while preparing the final three volumes of the series of Knuth's technical papers, namely Selected Papers on Design of Algorithms (published in 2009) Selected Papers on Fun and Games (published in 2010) Companion to the Papers of Donald Knuth (to be published in January 2011)
    Also included are relevant letters written back and forth since 2003, relating not only to the creation of the final three volumes but also to reprints of the first six, and translations into other languages.
    - DA02: The Bose--Nelson Sorting Problem P55 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      copy of original article; marked proofs; test of illustrations
    - DA03: A One-Way, Stackless Quicksort Algorithm P115 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      copy of original article; marked proofs
    - DA04: Optimum Binary Search Trees P41 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - DA05: Dynamic Huffman Coding P103 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - DA06: Inhomogeneous Sorting P92 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - DA07: Lexicographic Permutations with Restrictions P93 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - DA08: Nested Satisfiability P134 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - DA09: Fast Pattern Matching in Strings P71 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - DA10: Addition Machines P126 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - DA11: A Simple Program Whose Proof Isn't P133 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - DA12: Verification of Link-Level Protocols P99 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - DA13: A Problem in Concurrent Programming Control Q17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - DA14: Optimal Prepaging and Font Caching P105 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - DA15: A Generalization of Dijkstra's Algorithm P85 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - DA16: Two-Way Rounding P145 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - DA17: Matroid Partitioning R28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      copy of original tech report; marked proofs
    - DA18: Irredundant Intervals P151 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      copy of original article; copies of correspondence; marked proofs
    - DA19: Simple Word Problems in Universal Algebras P34 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - DA20: Efficient Representation of Perm Groups P123 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - DA21: An Algorithm for Brownian Zeros P107 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - DA22: Semi-Optimal Bases for Linear Dependencies P113 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - DA23: Evading the Drift in Floating-Point Addition P73 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - DA24: Deciphering a Linear Congruential Encryption P97 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - DA25: Computation of Tangent, Euler, and Bernoulli Numbers P27 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - DA26: Euler's Constant to 1271 Places P8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - DA27: Evaluation of Polynomials by Computer P9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - DA28: Minimizing Drum Latency Time P5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      copy of original article; marked proofs; appendix on modern solution
    - DA29: first draft of entire book, used to make the index (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - DA30: results of proofreading (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - FG00: Front matter (Box 1, Folder 30)
      early outline and notes; early drafts
    - FG01: The Potrzebie System of Weights and Measures P1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      marked proofs
    - FG02: Official Tables of the Potrzebie System 10p (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - FG03: The Revolutionary Potrzebie R4a (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - FG04: A {\mc MAD} Crossword 4p (Box 1, Folder 34)
      copy of original editorial correspondence from 1960; marked proofs and trials
    - FG06: The Complexity of Songs Q48 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - FG07: TPK in {\mc INTERCAL} 18p (Box 1, Folder 36)
      early draft notes; marked proofs
    - FG08: Math Ace: The Plot Thickens R4cd (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - FG09: Billiard Balls in an Equilateral Triangle P14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - FG10: Representing Numbers Using Only One 4 P18 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - FG11: Very Magic Squares P31 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - FG12: The Gamow--Stern Elevator Problem P35 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - FG13: Fibonacci Multiplication P117 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - FG14: A Fibonacci-Like Sequence of Composite Numbers P119 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - FG15: Transcendental Numbers Based on the Fibonacci Sequence P13 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      marked proofs; copy of recent research cited in addendum
    - FG16: Supernatural Numbers P95 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - FG17: Mathematical Vanity Plates Q210 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      proofs of illustrations; marked proofs
    - FG18: Diamond Signs 18p (Box 1, Folder 47)
      proofs of illustrations; handwritten drafts; marked proofs
    - FG19: The Orchestra Song 6p (Box 1, Folder 48)
      first proofs of music setting with METAPOST; marked proofs
    - FG20: Gnebbishland 4p (Box 1, Folder 49)
      handwritten MS; web research on nebbishes; correspondence; marked proofs
    - FG21: A Carol for Advent 3p (Box 1, Folder 50)
      original music and lyrics sent out Christmas 2001; marked proofs
    - FG22: Randomness in Music 6p (Box 1, Folder 51)
      proofs of illustrations; library search re Strindberg; marked proofs
    - FG23: Basketball's Electronic Coach 10p (Box 1, Folder 52)
      original notes; marked proofs; correspondence about players' names
    - FG24: The Triel: A New Solution P58 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - FG25: The Computer as Master Mind P81 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      marked proofs; correspondence re early sets and new results
    - FG26: Move It Or Lose It Q223 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      copy of original letter to Martin Gardner; marked proofs
    - FG27.1: Adventure 160p (Box 1, Folder 56)
      original CTWILLed program before converting to book pages
    - FG27.2: Adventure 160p (Box 1, Folder 57)
      early proofs of cave map; first version of the program in book-page format
    - FG27.3: Adventure 160p (Box 1, Folder 58)
      marked proofs of May 2010
    - FG28: Ziegler's Giant Bar 6p (Box 1, Folder 59)
      tests of illustrations; marked proofs; correspondence re Milwaukee TV etc; material from the dictionary I used in 1952; copies of news clippings
    - FG29: The Chemical Caper R4b (Box 1, Folder 60)
      marked proofs; info about original names of newly discovered elements
    - FG31: Disappearances Q54 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - FG32: Lewis~Carroll's word--ward--ware--dare--dame--game Q51 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - FG34: Biblical Ladders Q172 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - FG36: {\it Quadrata Obscura\/} (Hidden Latin Squares) Q224 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      words tests done while composing this puzzle
    - FG38: Dancing Links P159 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      marked proofs, before and after major changes
    - FG40: Uncrossed Knight's Tours Q23 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      samples of marked proofs and illustration tests as I was writing this chapter
    - FG41: Celtic Knight's Tours 21p (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - FG42: Long and Skinny Knight's Tours 29p (Box 2, Folder 1)